Finding Aid for Ann Arbor Private Hospital (Mich.) records, 1902-1933
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ann Arbor Private Hospital (Mich.) records 1902-1933
Ann Arbor Private Hospital (Mich.)
23 linear feet
87471 Bf.3 2
Hospital established by University of Michigan professor of obstetrics and gynecology, Reuben Peterson; until July 1917, it was called Peterson Hospital. Bound case files, miscellaneous statistics, correspondence, research material, and reprints of articles written by Peterson.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were deposited with the library by Dr. J. Robert Willson, Women’s Hospital, University of Michigan (donor no. 6740 ) on February 11, 1982.
No further additions to the records are expected.
Access to the record group is restricted. Records are closed for 100 years from the date of creation. Records older than 100 years may be open for research after the researcher has signed the Patient/Client Access Agreement.
The Peterson Hospital was founded in Ann Arbor in 1902 by Reuben Peterson, M.D., to provide a much needed facility for obstetric and gynecology cases. The hospital, which consisted of several houses on South Forest and South University, was called the Ann Arbor Private Hospital from 1917 to 1933. Besides his role as founder and chief of the medical staff at his private hospital, Dr. Peterson was Bates Professor of Diseases of Women and Children in the Department of Medicine and Surgery (Medical School), 1901-1922; Medical Director of the University of Michigan Hospital, 1912-1918; Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, 1922-1930; and historian of the University of Michigan Medical School.
The records consist largely of bound case histories for the years 1902-1933. The case histories include correspondence between physicians and patients, diagnostic notes and daily records of the patients' hospital stay. Dr. Peterson carried on some follow-up research, especially on prolapse cases. A listing of patient names and case numbers is on the flyleaf of each volume.
In addition, there is an account for the years, 1902-1921, documenting the founding, growth and diminution of the hospital and its training school for nurses. Several folders of correspondence of the University of Michigan Medical School Departments of Surgery and Obstetrics-Gynecology, some of Dr. Peterson's research material, and reprints of his articles complete the collection.
Subjects:
Gynecology.; Hospitals--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Medicine--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Peterson Hospital (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan--Faculty.; Ann Arbor Private Hospital (Mich.); Peterson, Reuben, 1862-1942.
- Gynecological cases, bound volumes
  - June 1902-October 1904 (Box 1)
    (Vol. nos. 1-3)
  - October 1904-January 1907 (Box 2)
    (Vol. nos. 4-6)
  - January 1907-November 1908 (Box 3)
    (Vol. nos. 7-9)
  - October 1908-April 1910 (Box 4)
    (Vol. nos. 10-15)
  - March 1910-September 1911 (Box 5)
    (Vol. nos. 16-21)
  - September 1911-April 1913 (Box 6)
    (Vol. nos. 22-27)
  - April 1913-March 1915 (Box 7)
    (Vol. nos. 28-34)
  - March 1915-March 1917 (Box 8)
    (Vol. nos. 35-41)
    [PR RESTRICTED until January 1, 2017 ]
  - March 1917-July 1918 (Box 9)
    (name changes to Ann Arbor Private Hospital, July 1917)
    (Vol. nos. 42-46)
    [PR RESTRICTED until January 1, 2018 ]
  - July 1918-December 1919 (Box 10)
    (Vol. nos. 47-50)
    [PR RESTRICTED until January 1, 2019 ]
  - January 1920-October 1921 (Box 11)
    (Vol. nos. 51-53)
    [PR RESTRICTED until January 1, 2021 ]
  - September 1921-August 1923 (Box 12)
    (Vol. nos. 54-56)
    [PR RESTRICTED until January 1, 2023 ]
  - July 1923-November 1925 (Box 13)
    (Vol. nos. 57-59)
    [PR RESTRICTED until January 1, 2025 ]
  - October 1926-January 1929 (Box 14)
    (Vol. nos. 61-63)
    [PR RESTRICTED until January 1, 2029 ]
  - January 1929-October 1930 (Box 15)
    (Volume 65 labeled "Ann Arbor Private Hospital Surgery")
    (Vol. nos. 64-65)
    [PR RESTRICTED until January 1, 2030 ]
  - Case files June 1931-April 1933, 5 folders (Box 15)
    [PR RESTRICTED until January 1, 2033 ]
- Maternity Cases, bound volumes
  - October 1913-October 1916 (Box 16)
    (Vol. nos. 1-4)
    [PR RESTRICTED until January 1, 2016 ]
  - October 1916-January 1919 (Box 17)
    (Vol. nos. 5-9)
  - February 1919-July 1921 (Box 18)
    (Vol. nos. 10-14)
  - June 1921-April 1926 (Box 19)
    (Vol. nos. 15-20)
    [PR RESTRICTED until January 1, 2026 ]
  - April 1926-March 1930 (Box 20)
    (Vol. nos. 21-25)
  - March 1930-March 1931 (Box 21)
    (Vol. nos. 26-27)
    [PR RESTRICTED until January 1, 2031 ]
  - March 1931-June 1933, 3 folders (Box 21)
- Other records
  - Statistics of hospital cases, operations 1903-1920 (Box 22)
  - Account, by year, of hospital facilities and staff 1902-1921 (Box 22)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box 22)
    - 1922, 1923 (Box 22)
    - January-June 1924 (Box 22)
    - July-December 1924 (Box 22)
    - January-June 1925 (Box 22)
    - July-December 1925 (Box 22)
    - 1926 (Box 22)
    - 1927 (Box 22)
    - 1928 (Box 22)
    - 1929 (Box 22)
  - Reprints 1920-1922 (Box 22)
  - Research undated (Box 22)
  - Research, private prolapse cases (Box 22)
  - Research, UM prolapse cases 1912 (Box 22)
  - Cancer statistics 1910, 1911 (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous statistics (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous (bibliography, letter to Detroit Free Press, 1906) (Box 22)
  - Maternity registers 1913-1933, 8 volumes (Box 23)